Guide to the Brainerd Currie Papers 1957-1960
University of Chicago Library
Currie, Brainerd. Papers
1957-1960
4 linear feet (8 boxes)
Hanna Holborn Gray Special Collections Research Center University of Chicago Library 1100 East 57th Street Chicago, Illinois 60637 U.S.A.
Brainerd Currie (1912-1965), Law Professor. The Papers consist primarily of articles written by Currie between 1957 and 1960. Included are drafts, notes, proofs and offrints, and related correspondence. Also in the collection are drafts of humorous poems and lyrics, including "The Rose of Aberlone."
Information on Use
Access
The collection is open for research.
Biographical Note
Brainerd Currie was born on December 20, 1912, in Macon Georgia. He graduated from Augusta Junior College, in Augusta Georgia, then received an LL.B. from Mercer University in 1935. He taught first at Mercer, then at Wake Forest College, before resuming his studies at Columbia Law School, where he earned an LL.M. in 1941 and a J.Sc.D. in 1955.
After briefly serving on the Law Faculty at the University of Georgia, Currie worked during World War II in the Offices of Price Administration and Economic Stabilization. From 1946 to 1949, he taught at Duke Law School. He joined the new Law Faculty at the University of California at Los Angeles in 1949, served briefly as Dean of the Law School at the University of Pittsburgh in 1952, then joined the faculty at the University of Chicago Law School, where he remained until returning to Duke in 1961. As a legal scholar, Currie was best known for study of conflict of laws, which arises when the laws of multiple countries or jurisdictions are in contradiction. He also penned nonsense verse and humorous lyrics, with legal themes, the best known of which is "The Rose of Aberlone."
Currie married Elmyr Park in 1935. The couple had three children, Elliott, Carolyn, and David, who also served on the Law Faculty of the University of Chicago. Currie died in Durham in 1965.
Scope Note
The Brainerd Currie Papers consist primarily of articles written by Currie between 1957 and 1960. Included are drafts, notes and related correspondence. Also in the collection are drafts of poems and lyrics, including "The Rose of Aberlone."
Related Resources
Browse finding aids by topic.
Subject Headings
Currie, Brainerd; University of Chicago. Law School; Law -- United States
INVENTORY
- "Attachment and Garnishment in the Federal Courts," correspondence and drafts, undated (Box 1, Folder 1-3)
- "Change of Venue and Conflict of Laws," correspondence, undated (Box 1, Folder 4)
- "Change of Venue and Conflict of Laws: A Retraction," draft, undated (Box 1, Folder 5)
- "The Constitution and the Conflict of Laws: Governmental Interests and the Judicial Function," drafts, undated (Box 1, Folder 6-7)
- "The Constitution and the Conflict of Laws: Governmental Interests and the Judicial Function," footnotes, undated (Box 1, Folder 8)
- "The Constitution and the ‘Transitory’ Cause of Action," drafts, circa 1959 (Box 2, Folder 1-4)
- "Purchase Money Mortgages and State Lines: A Study in Conflict of Laws," correspondence and drafts, 1959-1960 (Box 2, Folder 5-7)
- "Notes on Methods and Objectives in the Conflict of laws," draft, undated (Box 3, Folder 1)
- "Married Women’s Contracts," drafts, undated (Box 3, Folder 2-3)
- "Death Makes a Difference," correspondence and draft, 1960 (Box 3, Folder 4)
- "The Silver Oar and All That: A Study of the Romero Case," correspondence and drafts, undated (Box 3, Folder 5-8)
- "The Silver Oar and All That: A Study of the Romero Case," drafts, undated (Box 4, Folder 1-4)
- "The Silver Oar and All That: A Study of the Romero Case," footnotes, undated (Box 4, Folder 5)
- "The Silver Oar and All That: A Study of the Romero Case," notes and publications, undated (Box 4, Folder 6-7)
- "The Silver Oar and All That: A Study of the Romero Case," notes and publications, undated (Box 5, Folder 1-2)
- "Survival of Actions: Adjudication Versus Automation in the Conflict of Laws," drafts, 1954-1956, circa 1958 (Box 5, Folder 3-5)
- "Survival of Actions: Adjudication Versus Automation in the Conflict of Laws," notes and publications, 1957 (Box 5, Folder 6)
- "Unconstitutional Discrimination in the Conflict of Laws," correspondence and drafts, 1959-1960, undated (Box 6, Folder 1-8)
- Hill, Alfred, "Governmental Interest and the Conflict of Laws: A Reply to Professor Currie," typescript, undated (Box 7, Folder 1)
- "The Verdict of the Quiescent Years: Mr. Hill and the Conflict of Laws," drafts, undated (Box 7, Folder 2-3)
- "When is Foreign Law Material?" correspondence and notes, 1957-1958 (Box 7, Folder 4)
- "Walton v. Aramco," correspondence and drafts, 1958-1959 (Box 7, Folder 5-6)
- "Walton v. Aramco," correspondence and drafts, 1958-1959 (Box 8, Folder 1-2)
- "Conflict of Laws," book review, draft, undated (Box 8, Folder 3)
- "Foreign Law: A Guide to Pleading and Proof," book review, typescript, undated (Box 8, Folder 4)
- "The Law of Admiralty," book review, typescript, undated (Box 8, Folder 5)
- "The Rose of Aberlone," and other verse, undated (Box 8, Folder 6)
- Correspondence and notes, 1958 (Box 8, Folder 7)
- Reference material, 1950s (Box 8, Folder 8)